# Joel Worrall

717.385.9970 / joel@joelworrall.com / @tangollama

# Executive Management, Strategic Leadership, Brand Development, Innovation, Technology Product Development, Digital Transformation

## Summary

I started my career in the software industry as a programmer, architect, and consultant. A decade ago, I began to grow my skills in the areas of people management, organizational leadership, strategic planning, brand building, board engagement, and the business value of servant leadership.

Today, my experiences have equipped me with a team-oriented management philosophy and strategic execution experience at multiple levels. My goal is to invest my skills and management background in both the software and international nonprofit sectors to provide senior leadership to an organization with a mission I can embrace, a culture I can influence, a team I can pour into, and a vision I can help guide.

#### Education

Bachelor's in Computer Science, Messiah College, Grantham, PA (2000) Master's in Religion, Evangelical Theological Seminary, Myerstown, PA (2015)

#### Skills

- Management of departments across distributed offices, time zones, and continents
- Team leadership, mentoring staff and subordinates, managing up, and coaching peers
- Brand development and messaging
- Mass-marketing, messaging, and fundraising, including proposal creation and presentation
- Corporate strategic planning and execution with sustainable results
- Corporate culture leadership, embracing and setting pace for core values
- Personnel management, including restructuring organizational reporting relationships
- Talent identification, recruitment, and onboarding
- Volunteer recruitment and management, including open source software contributions
- Strong presentation, public speaking, and written communication skills
- A track record of creating, influencing and owning a vision for an organization
- Multi-million dollar budget management
- Nearly a decade of Board-level reporting experience

#### Experience

### CURE International (since 2009)

Member of the executive leadership team providing oversight and strategic direction to a global nonprofit healthcare organization with 1,500 employees and an operational presence in 29 countries.

<u>Chief Technology Officer and Office of the CEO</u> – June 2016 to present <u>Chief Technology Officer</u> – May 2014 to June 2016

#### <u>Vice President of Technology and Marketing</u> – July 2010 to May 2014

Vice President of Technology – October 2009 to July 2010

- Oversaw all technology, marketing, brand-building and creative efforts
- Led transition from traditional nonprofit software tools to a full cloud technology strategy
- Co-founded the award-winning <u>cure.org</u> and the <u>CUREkids</u> real-time field reporting platform
- Co-founded the HospitalRun open source software project
- Wrote and spoke for conferences and events across a variety of audiences and venues
- Conducted executive recruiting and management
- Directed crisis communications and public relations
- Authored and led the messaging, content, and execution for org's largest fundraising event
- Oversaw the growth of CURE's first, successful monthly recurring revenue program
- Directed the creation of CURE's content marketing strategy
- Serving as the lead executive and primary communicator through a CEO transition

#### HospitalRun (since 2014)

#### <u>Core Team [Volunteer]</u> – February 2014 to present

Co-founder of the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source health information platform, responsible for strategic direction, community management, messaging, code contributions, and reviewing pull requests.

#### Mzinga & KnowledgePlanet Inc. (3 years)

Led a 75-person engineering department of a venture-backed enterprise software company. Responsible for technology roadmap, product development, acquisition due diligence, and R&D.

Vice President, Engineering & Development – March 2009 to October 2009

Director of Engineering – August 2008 to March 2009

<u>Director of Development, Learning & Workplace Communities</u> – Feb. 2008 to Aug. 2008

Development Manager – Feb. 2007 to Feb. 2008

Software Architect – July 2006 to Jan. 2007

- Led shift of product architecture and business model from Application Service Provider to complete Software as a Service multi-tenant, single instance environment
- Provided technical leadership through a debt restructuring and recapitalization event
- Guided the engineering organization through the merger of three separate companies and development organizations as well as the incorporation of offshore, outsourced team
- Negotiated major software vendor contracts and services
- Performed technical diligence through acquisitions
- Implemented lightweight, effective performance review and project scheduling
- Served as consultant and solution architect, working with troubled client relationships

#### CommNav Inc. (3 years)

Lead Java developer of a 20-person startup focused on a business portal framework.

#### Lead Architect – July 2000 to April 2003

- Responsible for approving designs and documentation, overseeing and mentoring junior developers, and managing testing for all next-generation product development efforts
- Primary author of the development API's and system documentation